M. Adil Yalçın





December 2016

June 2010

June 2008

Visual Data Analyst, Consultant, Developer

Ph.D., Computer Science, University of Maryland, College Park

Lowering the barriers in rich visual & interactive data analysis for a broad audience is the driving motivation of my work. I am the designer and developer of **Keshif** (www.keshif.me), the next generation out-of-the-box rapid visual data exploration environment.

I offer professional data analysis services, consulting and development through Keshif, LLC. My solutions are based on innovative human-centered design, research, and engineering.

You can reach me at ■ adil@keshif.me or in (linkedin.com/in/adilyalcin). (I am a green card holder.)

Education



Doctor of Philosophy

Computer Science, University of Maryland, College Park, USA

Thesis: A Systematic and Minimalist Approach to Lower Barriers in Visual Data Exploration

Advisors: Niklas Elmqvist, Ben Bederson



Master of Science

Computer Engineering, Bilkent University, Ankara, Turkey

Thesis: Real-Time Simulation and Visualization of Deformations on Heightfields

Advisor: Bülent Özgüç, Co-Advisor: Tolga Çapın

Bachelor of Science

Computer Engineering, Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

Senior Project: Operational Simulation System - OPSIMUS



Goal

User Interfaces / Visualization / Front End / Design

Development

Data Processing / Back End

Computer Graphics, Simulation

Effective, minimal solutions to complex challenges

JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3, d3, Photoshop, Tableau

SublimeText, less, Version control (git/svn)

Node.js, SQL, Python, Java, Matlab

C++, C, OpenGL / GLSL, OpenCL / Cuda, Lua

Publications

AggreSet: Rich and Scalable Set Exploration using Visualizations of Element Aggregations

M. Adil Yalçın & Niklas Elmqvist & Ben Bederson

INFOVIS '15 - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. of the VAST / InfoVis / SciVis 2015)

Cognitive Stages in Visual Data Exploration

M. Adil Yalçın & Niklas Elmqvist & Ben Bederson

BELIV '16 - Proceedings of Beyond Time and Errors: Novel Evaluation Methods for Visualization at IEEE VIS 2016

Keshif: Out-of-the-Box Visual and Interactive Data Exploration Environment

M. Adil Yalçın & Niklas Elmqvist & Ben Bederson

VIP '16 - Visualization In Practice Workshop at IEEEVIS

Information Visualization

M. Adil Yalçın & Catherine Plaisant

Big Data and Social Sciences - CRC Publishing

PixelPie: Maximal Poisson-disk Sampling with Rasterization

Cheuk Yiu Ip & M. Adil Yalçın & David Luebke & Amitabh Varshney

HPG '13 - Proceedings of the 5th High-Performance Graphics Conference

GPU Algorithms for Diamond-based Multiresolution Terrain Processing

M. Adil Yalçın & Kenneth Weiss & Leila De Floriani

EGPGV '11 - Proceedings of the 11th Eurographics conference on Parallel Graphics and Visualization

Incorporating Learning Analytics into Basic Course Administration: How to Embrace the Opportunity to Identify Inconsistencies and Inform Responses

Lindsey B. Anderson & Elizabeth E. Gardner & Andrew D. Wolvin & Rowena Kirby-Straker & Adil Yalcin & Ben Bederson

NCA 2015 - 101th Annual meeting of the National Communication Association

Real-Time Simulation and Visualization of Deformations on Heightfields

M. Adil Yalçın

M.Sc. Thesis - Bilkent University

A Generic Multi-View Rendering Engine Architecture

M. Adil Yalçın & Tolga Çapın

Game Engine Gems Volume 2 - A.K. Peters

Route Visualization in Indoor Panoramic Imagery with Open Area Maps

Mateis Stroila & M. Adil Yalcin & Joe Mays & Narayanan Alwar

ICMEW '12 - IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo Workshops

Editing Heightfield using History Management and 3D Widgets

M. Adil Yalçın & Tolga Çapın

ISCIS '09 - 24th International Symposium on Computer and Information Sciences

Work Experience

START (National Consortium for the Study of Terrorism and Responses to Terrorism) - College 2016 - now Park, MD

Research & Development > Global Terrorism Database

SESYNC (National Socio-Environmental Synthesis Center) - Annapolis, MD

Research & Development > Data to Motivate Synthesis

Teaching and Learning Transformation Center, UMD - College Park, MD

Research & Development > Education Data Analysis

AT&T Labs Research - Florham Park, New Jersey

R&D Internship > Free viewpoint synthesis using depth and color sensors

2014 - 2015

2015 - 2016

2012 Summer